hey guys this is a very short
announcement about our first online
course which is called sense making 101
and it's something that we're really
excited about working on for quite a
while thinking about it for a very long
time and then working on it for quite a
while it feels very natural for us to
move into this area because we've always
been talking about the value of practice
the value of living out some of the
ideas rather than just listening to them
and we're really excited because we have
a really great faculty onboard to help
us teach the course and so yeah you want
to talk more about what people are going
to learn on sense-making 101 so we put a
lot of time and thought into designing
this course and probably the easiest way
to describe it is that it moves from the
inside out so the more we've explored
concepts like sense-making or collective
intelligence on the channel the more
it's become clear that in order for that
to happen in order for us to have you
know emerging conversations or
conversations that go somewhere that we
might not be expecting there's actually
a toolkit of skills we need to let's say
play in that space one of them is
sovereignty so this is a concept we've
talked about a few times and this is
that sense of being connected to
yourself so having discernment and
knowing who I am where I'm going and
almost being sufficient to yourself but
at the same time being open and
receptive to your environment so that's
a really core concept because that keeps
us grounded and then as well there's
another concept which is the shadow so
the shadow we've talked about quite a
lot and that's the shadow is all the
aspects of ourselves that we are
rejecting in some way and why it's
important for this and for sense-making
is that if there's some aspects of
ourselves that were just completely
unaware of they come out sideways as we
say so that means that we can't really
enter into a genuine authentic dialogue
because there's always some aspect of
ourselves we're not fully bringing into
it and so we're not quite complete so
that's really key that we work through
that and then as well there's a concept
of agency so that we know that we are
thinking for ourselves moving in a
direction that we're choosing and then
once we've got these kind of inner
skills we can start expanding it out so
then we start looking at sense making so
looking at how do I make sense of the
world how do I discern by myself and
then how do I do that with others
there's two quite different things for
me to have a sense of okay I've done my
research I know
I'm being discerning when I'm looking at
safe you know news online but when we
come together and start trying to make
sense of the world together lots of new
dynamics come out it becomes a lot more
complex so to do that we have we have to
look at okay how do group dynamics works
how does inter relation work and how do
we come in and out of coherence and
what's that process like so we become
skilled at that as well and then we
start looking even further taking
another step back and looking at what
are the value structures we're working
within what's our environment what are
the wider systems that play so the hope
is and our intention is that we go on
that journey from the inside to the out
and we develop a lot of core skills
along the way that we can then bring
into our lives yeah and I think it's
important to say that we've been running
retreats together like we both train
ders as counselors a couple of years ago
we've been running retreat together
mainly men's retreats this is not going
to be a men only course it's gonna be a
mixed course and so we've got some
experience with doing that in real life
and now we're trying to bring it a bit
more into the ideas that we've got on
the channel and then into the sort of
the wider online community and but we're
not doing it alone we've got an amazing
faculty who are gonna be helping us out
with it as well and we wanted to play
some clips from each of them to give it
a bit more of a sense of what they'll be
delivering on the course so we're gonna
start with someone a lot of people might
be familiar with daniel trachtenberg our
earnestness and sincerity empowered by
really deep courage and a deep kind of
epistemic humility is going to make
someone misfit for every end group
currently which is the valley crossing
that people have to go through to
basically leave the forces that are
irate arrayed in a war that we're all
sides are wrong to hopefully have enough
people who do that that start to find
each other and don't do a new tribal
groupthink thing but all engage in
earnest actual thinking themselves an
actual conversation without orienting
towards groupthink that can start to
make a new strange attractor so another
favorite the channel is John vivace he's
become a kind of bit of a cult hit
online with his awakening from the
meaning crisis series and I went out
recently and spending
time with him in Toronto and recorded
this filled that will be going out in
the next couple of days where he talks
about and this is what is me talking
about in the course is wisdom what is
wisdom and how do we embody it because
it's much more than just a cognitive or
an ideas based thing what is
self-deception what are higher states of
consciousness what is enlightenment what
is wisdom what's our best cognitive
scientific answer that and then can we
use that to create what I call psycho
technologies and communities and
ecologies of them that can give us back
the cultivation of wisdom and self
transcendence and also connect us up to
a world of you that valorizes homes
legitimates and make sense of that set
of practices so we also have Diane musho
Hamilton who's an award-winning mediator
and also a meditation instructor and
Diane has a lot of expertise around the
area of collective intelligence and in
this clip she's talking about this other
aspect that's quite closely related to
it which is coherence and about how this
process of being in and out of coherence
and the difference between coherence and
difference is really essential for
collective intelligence my experiences
create a lot of coherence and then
heightened difference boom and then you
start to experience emergence and how to
heighten difference is the skill set
we're always trying to move everybody
towards sameness and we're trying to
move everybody towards coherence but
actually what we need to be doing is
helping people calibrate and move
together highly coherently and then
really experience difference as it
arises on an embodied level within the
interaction notice when it flips into
threat and try to calibrate difference
and teach people how to be in difference
because that's where emergence is more
likely to to really make itself to
really come forward as to this collision
of difference that's what happens and we
also have raffia Morgan who has been on
the channel a couple of times we're
actually gonna bring out another film
with him pretty soon early in the new
year an amazing facilitator a longtime
friend and a mentor of ours on rebel
wisdom it has become kind of central to
the work that I do where I try and
are people to get in touch with that
inner longing or urge and let it guide
them and I really trust this is like one
of the most precious things we have
inside that longing we'll take you where
you need to go so if I'm longing for
freedom which I am it doesn't take me
necessarily to freedom it takes me in
the direction of freedom but it takes me
to those places inside of myself where
I've cut myself off from freedom where I
put up a barrier so the longing is very
it's very precise if you really feel it
it takes you where you need to go where
you need to go is where you shut down
and then we also have dough Xin Roshi
who is delivering a session on the
shadow which is a really core concept
and one he's really an expert in fact
he's known as the shadow Roshi so play
clip from him we have to have collective
ways of dealing with this collective
shadow and we've developed some some
collective shadow work some group shadow
work where we we really talk about these
shadows and we work on them and we help
people become conscious of them so we
thought long and hard about how to
structure the course in the best way and
what we're gonna deliver is an
eight-week process and it's really a mix
of working together so working in small
groups having sessions with a live
lesson and Q&A with a teacher also
access anytime you want to exclusive
interviews we've recorded with them and
as well as that we have a pretty
detailed course booklet so you can do
kind of further your study as you have
time to do so throughout the whole
course the course will be starting at
the beginning of March and there will be
limited places you've got any queries
about it we've just created an email
address for it that's going to appear on
screen now unless I forget and so if you
want to ask any more questions about it
just send us an email to that and yeah
go to the website the website is in the
show notes below and hope to see you
soon
you